Guide to the Dorothy Whitlock papers, 1948-1989 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Dorothy Whitlock papers 1948-1989 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Whitlock, Dorothy.
1.5 Linear Feet Approx. 300 Items
Occupational therapist and medical illustrator active in Utah and North Carolina.
The Dorothy Whitlock Papers span the dates 1948-1989 and derive from Whitlock's work as an occupational therapist and medical illustrator. The collection contains visual materials which include image files and loose images of medical illustrations in a variety of media, including but not limited to watercolor, graphite pencil, brushed graphite paint, pen and ink drawings, photographs of etchings, and photographs. The images include but are not limited to portrayals of various medical procedures, conditions, techniques, and tools. The collection also contains papers related to Whitlock's time as an occupational therapist at the Veterans' Administration Hospital in Oteen, North Carolina, and papers related to her interest in and work on tuberculosis. Acquired as part of the History of Medicine Collections at Duke University.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Dorothy Whitlock papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a transfer from the Medical Center Library in 2011.
Biographical Note
Dorothy Whitlock (1894-1989) was the Director of Occupational Therapy at the State Tuberculosis Sanatorium in Ogden, Utah and later worked as an occupational therapist at the Veterans' Administration Hospital in Oteen, North Carolina. Whitlock was also a talented medical illustrator and created many illustrations of medical procedures, conditions, tools, and other images relating to the practice of medicine.
Collection Overview
The Dorothy Whitlock Papers span the dates 1948-1989 and derive from Whitlock's work as an occupational therapist and medical illustrator. The collection contains visual materials which include image files and loose images of medical illustrations in a variety of media, including but not limited to watercolor, graphite pencil, brushed graphite paint, pen and ink drawings, photographs of etchings, and photographs. The images include but are not limited to portrayals of various medical procedures, conditions, techniques, and tools. The collection also contains notebooks created during Whitlock's time at the Veterans' Administration Hospital in Oteen, North Carolina, where she practiced as an occupational therapist.
Additional items include professional materials, including professional files and loose professional materials containing undated in-service notes on tuberculosis, notes and papers from the National Tuberculosis Association's conferences in 1948, 1950, 1951, and 1952 in Salt Lake City, Utah, planning materials for an occupational therapy convention in Glenwood Spring, Colorado in 1950, including correspondence and papers, and additional loose notes relating to Whitlock's work.
Acquired as part of the History of Medicine Collections at Duke University.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Whitlock, Dorothy
National Tuberculosis Association -- History
Oteen Veteran's Administration Hospital
Medical illustration
Military hospitals, North Carolina
Occupational therapy -- United States
Tuberculosis -- United States
Women in medicine -- United States
Etchings
Photographs
Watercolors (paintings)
History of Medicine Collections (Duke University)
Contents of Collection
- Notebooks Series, 1950-1952 and undated, (1 box, 4 folders)
  The notebooks were created during Dorothy Whitlock's time at the Veterans' Administration Hospital in Oteen, North Carolina, and contain Whitlock's manuscript notes on various topics in medicine taken in an unknown context, graphite sketches of medical procedures and practices, and notes on crafts such as weaving, beading, and leather work. Arranged alphabetically by title.
  - Notes on craft projects, Occupational Therapy Department, V.A. Hospital, Oteen, North Carolina (Box 1)
  - Notes, V.A. Hospital, Oteen, North Carolina, 1950-1952, (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Sketchbook from V.A. Hospital, Oteen, North Carolina (Box 1)
    About 75 pages with graphite sketches of medical procedures and handwritten notes.
- Professional Materials Series, 1948-1967 and undated, (1 box)
  Contains professional files and loose professional materials including conference materials, in-service notes and lecture materials as well as some graphite sketches and correspondence.
  - Utah, 1948-1950 (Box 2)
    Handwritten, undated notes on tuberculosis as well as typescript lectures and other materials regarding the treatment of persons afflicted with tuberculosis.
  - Glenwood Springs, Colorado, occupational therapy convention, 1950 (Box 2)
    Includes correspondence from Barbara Small to Dorothy Whitlock, handwritten notes regarding planning the convention, Dorothy Whitlock's travel arrangements, and printed notes on admission requirements from the American Occupational Therapy Association.
  - In-service notes, circa 1950-1955 (Box 2)
    Taken in unknown context; notes relate to the treatment of tuberculosis.
  - Service recognition programs at the V.A. Hospital in Oteen, North Carolina, 1959-1967 (Box 2)
    Typescript programs from various service recognition award ceremonies; Whitlock's name appears in recognition of her service to the V.A. hospital.
  - Notes and sketches, undated (Box 2)
    Contains handwritten notes from an unknown medical context and graphite sketches of various medical procedures.
  - Educational materials, 1989 and undated (Box 2)
    Geometry sketches, diagrams of male pelvis and examples of cancer to kidney. Latest date is emergency phone number public advertisement, clipped from phonebook.
- Visual Materials Series, 1963-1969 and undated, (3 boxes)
  Contains drawings, paintings, sketches, and photograps of medical illustrations, many of which are signed by Dorothy Whitlock. These images include a variety of media, including brushed graphite paint, watercolor, graphite pencil, and photographic prints. Sizes range from 8x11" to larger panels.
  - Illustrations Notebooks and Files Subseries, undated
    Contains sketches, drawings, and paintings of medical procedures, medical disorders and conditions, and medical tools, accompanied in some cases by notes; all or almost all executed by Dorothy Whitlock.
    - Drawings of the heart and other images, undated (Box 2)
      Contains 46 labeled photograph reproductions of images, possibly etchings, pasted onto individual pages. Includes a 1 page type-script manuscript in German showing a few of the images as they appear in an unidentified text.
    - Hands and instruments, undated (Box 2)
      Includes graphite sketches, watercolor paintings, pen and ink drawings. Images depict various surgical procedures, medical instruments, and unidentified conditions.
    - Watercolors, sketches, and notes, undated (Box 3)
      Contains 25 items, including graphite sketches, watercolors, and manuscript notes by an unidentified artist or artists.
  - Loose Illustrations Subseries, 1963-1969 and undated
    Contains medical illustrations created by Dorothy Whitlock in a variety of media, including but not limited to brushed graphite and watercolors. Materials are arranged chronologically, with undated materials appearing alphabetically by title at the end of the subseries.
    - Transplantation of the ureter to the dkin, Talmadge Hospital, Drs. Rinker and Mingledorf, 1963, (1 brushed graphite painting) (Box 3)
    - Scapula, 1966, (1 brushed graphite painting) (Box 3)
    - Unknown surgical procedure, 1966, (1 brushed graphite painting) (Box 3)
    - Heart, 1967, (1 watercolor) (Box 4)
    - Closure of colostomy, 1968, (1 brushed graphite painting) (Box 4)
    - Foetus, 1969, (1 brushed graphite painting) (Box 4)
    - Eye, undated, (1 watercolor) (Box 4)
    - Kidney with tumor, undated, (1 brushed graphite painting) (Box 4)
    - Skeleton, undated, (1 black and white photograph) (Box 4)